Guide to the James Merriam Howard Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
James Merriam Howard papers
1916-1969
MS 471
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.75
Correspondence, diaries, and other papers of the Rev. James Merriam Howard, chaplain to the 304th Field Artillery during World War I. The bulk of the papers cover the years 1917-1919 and relate to his service in the war and to his diary.
Howard, James M. (James Merriam), 1886-1971
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of James M. Howard.
Scope and Contents
The Howard collection (contained in two boxes) comprises material pertaining to the Reverend Howard's service during World War I and is arranged in four series:
Series I. General Correspondence.
This includes letters to his family from the front (1917-1919), and a sampling of other personal letters -- "ancient and recent, which the chaplain has cherished" (1916-1969).
Series II. Notebook Diary (1918).
This includes the original manuscript notebook diary, covering the period April - December 1918; a copy of the typewritten and annotated transcription; and miscellaneous correspondence relating to Howard's painstaking research in preparing this annotated version.
Series III. 304th Field Artillery Materials.
This includes newsletters from the front; 304th Field Artillery Association bulletins; and copies of the Association's publication, "The Pirate Piece."
Series IV. Personal and Memorabilia.
This includes a miniature pocket diary (1918); the contents of a scrapbook (1917-1919): and a number of photographs, newspaper clippings, and similar items.
Biographical / Historical
James Merriam Howard was born in 1886 in Montclair, New Jersey. He attended the public schools there, spent a year and a half at Andover, and received his B.A. from Yale in 1909. Following graduation he served for one year as Secretary of the Yale University Christian Association ("Dwight Hall") He then spent a year in Europe as a private tutor to an American schoolboy. After his return to the United States Howard prepared for the ministry at Union Theological Seminary, receiving his B.D. in 1914. He was ordained to the ministry on June 21st of that year and was installed soon thereafter as pastor at Bedford Park Presbyterian Church.
On September 11, 1917, Howard was commissioned Chaplain (with the rank of First Lieutenant) and was assigned to the 304th Field Artillery. He was promoted to Captain in March 1919, and served as Acting Senior Chaplain of the 77th Division from March 10th to May 10th of that year. Following his discharge from the United States Army Howard returned to his Bedford Park pastorate and was then called to the South Street Presbyterian Church of Morristown, New Jersey, where he served as pastor until 1936. From that date, and until his retirement in 1951, Howard was associated with the First Presbyterian Church in Fort Pierce, Florida.
Arrangement
Arranged in four series: I. General Correspondence. II. Notebook Diary (1918). III. 304th Field Artillery Materials. IV. Personal and Memorabilia.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
World War, 1914-1918; United States -- Foreign relations; Diaries; Clergy; Howard, James M. (James Merriam), 1886-1971; United States. Army. Field Artillery, 304th, 1917-1919
- GENERAL CORRESPONDENCE, Series I
  - Howard, G. H. (60), 1917-1919 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Howard, John and Susan (23), 1917-1919 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous "cherished letters" (19), 1916-1919, 1935, 1956, 1960, 1967-1969 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- NOTEBOOK DIARY (1918), Series II
  - Original Diary, April - December 1918 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Annotated transcript, pp. 1-51 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Annotated transcript, pp. 52-100 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Annotated transcript, pp. 101-150 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Annotated transcript, pp. 151-193 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence relating to the Diary [A - J], 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence relating to the Diary [K - Z], 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- 304th FIELD ARTILLERY MATERIALS, Series III
  - Newsletters to 304th Field Artillery Association, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Newsletter to Bedford Park Presbyterian Church (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 304th Field Artillery Association Bulletins [printed] (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - "An Experience with a Pirate Piece" (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "The Pirate Piece" (1929, 1935, 1966-1969) (Box 1, Folder 15)
- PERSONAL AND MEMORABILIA, Series IV
  - Miniature Pocket Diary (1918) (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Scrapbook (1917) (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Scrapbook (1918) (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Scrapbook (1919) (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Miscellaneous memorabilia (Box 2, Folder 22)